A Finding Aid to the Ezio Martinelli papers circa 1944-1973, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ezio Martinelli papers
circa 1944-1973
Archives of American Art
Martinelli, Ezio, 1913-1980
AAA.martezio
Archival Resource Key
2.4 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor and painter Ezio Martinelli measure 2.4 linear feet and date from circa 1944-1973. They illustrate his career through biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, and printed and photographic material.
Biographical / Historical
Ezio Martinelli (1913-1980) was a painter and sculptor who worked mainly in New York.
Martinelli was born on November 27 in West Hoboken New Jersey. He studied at the Academy of Fine Arts, Bologna. He then returned to the United States and from 1932 to 1936 studied at the National Academy of Design in New York with Leon Kroll and Gifford Beal studying drawing with Ivan Olinsky and sculpture with Robert Aiken.
Martinelli taught at the Philadelphia Museum School, Sarah Lawrence College, Parsons School of Design, the American Academy at Rome, and the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture. He participated in the Federal art project Works Progress Administration (WPA) from 1937 to 1941 as an easel painter and unit supervisor. His works can be found in multiple museums and organizations including the United Nations, The Art Institute of Chicago, the Brooklyn Museum of Art, The Whitney Museum of American Art, and the New York Public Library.
Martinelli died in 1980 in Saugerties, New York.
Arrangement
This collection consists of five series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1971 (.1 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1957-1972 (.3 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, circa 1962-1966 (.1 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, circa 1945-1970 (1.1 Linear feet: Boxes 1-2)
Series 5: Photographic Material, circa 1944-1969 (.8 Linear feet: Boxes 2-3, OV 4)
Scope and Contents
The Ezio Martinelli papers measure 2.4 linear feet and date from circa 1944-1973. Biographical materials contain Martinelli's resume. Correspondence is with various museums, galleries, and other organizations. Personal business records contain receipts for artwork shipments and travel documents. Printed material consists of exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and various publications. Photographic material consists of photographs of Martinelli and his artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papers were donated in 1972 and 1974 by Ezio Martinelli.
Related Materials
Ezio Martinelli's papers can also be found at Syracuse University.
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York
- Biographical Material, circa 1971; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials contain Martinelli's resume.
  - Resume, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, circa 1957-1972; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; .3 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is with various museums, art galleries, foundries, colleges and universities, businesses, and other organizations.
  - Correspondence, circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, circa 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, circa 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, circa 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - American Academy In Rome, circa 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - National Council For United States Art, circa 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - United Nations Sculpture, circa 1959-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Projects and Juries, circa 1962-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1962-1966; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 1
  Personal business records contain receipts for artwork shipments and travel documents.
  - Overseas Travel, circa 1962-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Receipts For Artwork Shipments, circa 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Printed Material, circa 1945-1970; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Printed material consists of exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and various publications relating to artwork as well as a copy of American Academy in Rome Report 1959-1964 (1964), and John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation 1961 and 1962 Reports of the President and of the Treasurer (1962).
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1940s), circa 1945-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1950s), circa 1956-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1960s), circa 1960-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1960s), circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1960s), circa 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1960s), circa 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1970s), circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Undated Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1945-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - American Academy in Rome Report 1959-1964 (1964), circa 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation 1961 and 1962 Reports of the President and of the Treasurer (1962), circa 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Art Publications, circa 1956-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Magazines, circa 1961-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ceremony Programs And Invitations, circa 1961-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, circa 1954-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photographic Material, circa 1944-1969; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; .8 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, OV 4
  Photographic material consists of photographs of Martinelli and his artwork.
  - Ezio Martinelli, circa 1950-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1944-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11-17)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1944-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1944-1969; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)